Guide to the Julia Dorn Heflin papers, 1919-1990 MVC0059.MS
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Julia Dorn Heflin papers
1919-1990
1950-1970
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MVC0059.MS
1.5 Linear Feet 3 document boxes
The Julia Dorn Heflin papers consist of material relating to her career at Mount Vernon College and her external work in the theater arts community of Washington, DC. Heflin was Director of the Drama and Speech department at Mount Vernon College and as faculty advisor to the popular "Prep Players" and "Curtain Callers" student theater groups. This collection consists of Heflin's personal and professional correspondence, performance programs and scripts, clippings, material relating to development of classes in speech and drama and her work with theater organizations. The inclusive dates of the collection are 1911-1990, with the bulk of the material dating from the 1950s and 1960s.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into two series: Mount Vernon professional work and Personal correspondence and outside activities.
Biographical / Historical
Julia Dorn Heflin (1911-2007) served in many capacities during her 22 year tenure at Mount Vernon College. She was hired in 1956 as Director of the Speech and Drama Department at Mount Vernon, a position which she held until 1977, when she was named Professor Emeritus. She also served as Faculty Advisor to the popular student theater groups "The Prep Players" and "The Curtain Callers."
Prior to her arrival at Mount Vernon, Heflin was active in theater production in other cities. Beginning in the 1930s, she acted and worked on Broadway, and also staged a theater production in Moscow, Russia. She co-founded the Bucks County Playhouse (PA) and also served as its company manager and director. In addition, she had a career in journalism, interviewing theater performers for "Stage Magazine" and working as a researcher and writer for the CBS radio program "We, The People."
During her tenure at Mount Vernon, Heflin directed more than 80 stage productions at Mount Vernon. Heflin also served on the Advisory Committee to the Mount Vernon College Arts and Humanities program. During her career, she was actively involved in many theater and arts organizations beyond the Mount Vernon campus.
After her retirement, she worked tirelessly to ensure that the drama program continued at Mount Vernon. She maintained contact with Mount Vernon alumnae and drama students from other colleges and universities regarding their theater careers.
Julia Dorn Heflin died in Washington, DC, in August 2007 at the age of 96.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, performance programs and scripts, newspaper clippings, conference and meeting programs, and photographs. The material dates from 1919-1990, with the bulk of the material dating from the 1950s and 1960s. These are the papers of Julia Dorn Heflin, who served as Director of Speech and Drama at Mount Vernon College from 1956-1978. Heflin was also the producer of many theater performances at Mount Vernon while serving as Faculty Advisor to the Prep Players and Curtain Callers student theater groups. Some material in this collection is also generated from Heflin's affiliation with outside theater organizations and her personal correspondence with Mount Vernon alumnae and others in the theater world.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Collection acquired by GWU upon merger with Mount Vernon College. Collection transferred to Foggy Bottom campus.
Drama; Theater management; Student organizations; Plays (document genre); Performances; Performing arts; Theater; Mount Vernon Seminary; Mount Vernon College; Julia Dorn Heflin
- Mount Vernon professional work, 1919-1987; Series 1; 1 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials relating to Heflin's various roles at Mount Vernon, including as Director and Instructor of Speech and Drama and as creator and advisor to the student led theater groups, the Prep Players and Curtain Callers. Also found in this series are materials relating to her role as member of the Advisory Committee to the Arts and Humanities Program at Mount Vernon. Material in Series 1 is arranged alphabetically by folder title. It contains performance programs and scripts, newspaper clippings relating to theater performances, and correspondence relating to her professional work at Mount Vernon.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - Clippings, 12/19/1956-04/21/1963; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clippings, 04/26/1963-04/1986; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 05/05/1960-04/21/1969; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 11/28/1970-11/29/1979; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 07/06/1956-10/21/1958; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 02/29/1980-03/11/1987; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Costume Sketches, 1950; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Curtain Callers, Constitution, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Curtain Callers Roll, 1965-1966; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Julia Dorn Heflin Self-Evaluation, 1974-1975; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Lists of Mount Vernon College Students, 1956-1964; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Mount Vernon Publications, 1925-1986; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mount Vernon Assembly Program, 1957-1958; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Mount Vernon College Arts and Humanities Faculty Meeting Minutes, 11/22/1985; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Mount Vernon College Arts and Humanities Program Publication, "Musings", circa 1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mount Vernon College Arts and Humanities Program Reports, 1978-1981; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Mount Vernon College Course Development and Planning, 1957-1986; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Notes, undated; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Performance Announcements--Dance At Mount Vernon, circa 1980; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Performance Announcements and Invitations, 1965-1972; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Performance Programs, 1941; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Performance Programs, 1950; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Performance Programs, 1951; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Performance Programs, 1954; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Performance Programs, 1955; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Performance Programs, 1956; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Performance Programs, 1957; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Performance Programs, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Performance Programs, 1959; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Performance Programs, 1960; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Performance Programs, 1961; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Performance Programs, 1962; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Performance Programs, 1963; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Performance Programs, 1964; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Performance Programs, 1965; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Performance Programs, 1966; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Performance Programs, 1967; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Performance Programs, 1968; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Performance Programs, 1969; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Performance Programs, 1970; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Performance Programs, 1971; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Performance Programs, 1984; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Performance Programs, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Performance Scripts, 1919-1931; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Performance Scripts, 1935-1937; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Performance Scripts, 1941-1970; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Performance Scripts, undated; Series 1 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Performance Script-"Alice in Wonderland", 1951; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Prep Players Account Book and Receipts, 1956-1964; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Prep Players Cast List "You Can't Take It With You", 1960; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Prep Players Evaluation, 11/24/1957; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Prep Players, Statement of Purpose, 02/1958; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Rehearsal Schedules, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Slides, "Carnival", 05/1969; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Speeches, undated; Series 1 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Personal correspondence and outside activities, 1955-1990; Series 2; 0.5 Linear Feet
  This series contains Heflin's personal correspondence and material generated from her involvement with activities external to Mount Vernon. Her correspondence includes letters to and from alumnae, cards and notes, recommendation letters for alumnnae and also for students at other colleges. This series also contains material generated from Heflin's involvement with external theater organizations, including conference programs, and newspaper clippings and correspondence with individuals in the theater community. Material in Series 2 is arranged alphabetically by folder title.
  - Articles, Miscellaneous Subjects, 1979-1984; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Clippings, Theater, 05/1961-09/1961; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Constitution, American Educational Theatre Association, Inc., 12/30/1959; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Cum Laude Society Handbook, 1963; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Julia Dorn Heflin, Receipt from Adams Teachers Agency, Inc., 09/29/1955; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Mayoral Proclamation, American Educational Theatre Association, Inc. Conference, 08/21/1961; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Mount Vernon College Alumnae Resume, circa 1981; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Performance Announcements, undated; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Personal Correspondence, cards, 1966-1990; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Personal Correspondence, Christmas Cards, circa 1965-1983; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Personal Correspondence, Letters of recommendation, 04/14/1964-02/07/1969; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Personal Correspondence, regarding Theater Conferences, 04/29/1965-06/18/1970; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Personal Correspondence with Mount Vernon alumnae, 05/28/1967-04/15/1981; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Personal Correspondence with Olwen Lloyd, 1972-1979; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Personal Correspondence with Theater Groups, 03/29/1961-01/04/1984; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Programs, Theater Conferences, 08/24/1961-08/17/1977; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Report and Code, Secondary School Theatre Conference, 12/1959; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Theater Workshop Summary, undated; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Transcripts, Theater Conference Sessions, 08/28/1961-10/29/1961; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 28)